<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Seconauts | Mark Curphey]]></title>
  <link href="http://curphey.github.com/blog/categories/seconauts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://curphey.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-04T14:42:10-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://curphey.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Curphey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Investing in developing software security talent]]></title>
    <link href="http://curphey.github.com/blog/2012/10/19/investing-in-software-security-talent/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-19T09:18:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://curphey.github.com/blog/2012/10/19/investing-in-software-security-talent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every single person I speak to in the software security industry agrees on one thing. There is a talent war. Put another way the demand for good software security people far outstrips the supply,  or yet another way there aren't enough people to secure the software that needs to be secured for the digital economy to continue to growing at the current rate. I could go on but you get the point. This is of course not a security industry issue but a general software engineering issue, amplified in niche areas and the dial turned right up to eleven for 'red hot' niches like security. Most companies approach the issue by making their company a more attractive place to work. Bigger salaries, better perks and a better work environment. If you judged the state of the economy by the amount of recruiter calls you would think we are in boom times. <!--more--></p>

<p>A few days ago I watched the Presidential debate. Inspired by Barack Obamas speech about investing in education to create a workforce with the skills that are in demand I started thinking about ways the security industry could invest to create the talent that is clearly in such high demand. I was thrown out of high-school at 17 (sixth form college in the UK) for being a generally naughty boy but after working it out of my system (yes "my" system not "the" system) I returned to formal education in my mid-twenties ending up with a Bachelors degree in engineering and a Masters Degree in Information Security where I specialized in cryptography at the Mathematics department of a top British University; Royal Holloway and Bedford New College, University of London. Despite being very proud of my academic achievement and appreciative of the doors that it undoubtedly opened, I can't help also acknowledge that relatively little of what I learned at college has been used in my career. I wouldn't change a thing (my 'no regrets' rule of life) but I often wonder how life might have been different if I had found a mentor in the security industry or had found an apprenticeship instead. I love the idea of mentors and apprenticeships and clearly others do as well. Last year <a href="http://www.livingsocial.com">Living Social</a> invested in growing talent this way by creating the <a href="http://hungryacademy.com/">Hungry Academy</a>.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='I have an idea. I think a software security mentor and internship program done right would have a meaningful impact on the industry'>I have an idea. I think a software security mentor and internship program done right would have a meaningful impact on the industry and I would invest time and money in making it happen as a core Seconauts project starting in the new year. I have spoken to a few people about this offline but before I start calling around and actually asking people if they will commit money and time I wanted to get some broader feedback as to whether companies would be willing to sponsor it and if mentors would be willing to invest their time in mentoring candidates.</span></p>

<p><strong>How would it work?</strong></br>
<strong>What's in it for sponsors?</strong></br>
<strong>What's in it for candidates?</strong></br>
<strong>What's in it for mentors?</strong></br></p>

<p><strong>How would it work?</strong>
I don't have a detailed plan (yet). This idea has been conceived over the last few days but I think it might work something like this.</p>

<p>Companies sponsor the Seconauts non-profit 501(3)c being setup for about $10,00 USD for each year they wish to support the program. There would be two, six month internship periods each year. Each Intern gets assigned (or chooses) four mentors. The primary mentor would be their 'go-to' person. I really don't like the term life coach but it maybe appropriate here. They would focus on the career, business and industry skills and provide continuity across the program. The primary mentor would also provide a physical workspace for the Intern at their company and the Intern would be expected to be physically present Monday-Friday. This will likely mean relocating for the period of the Internship, a small but important commitment for serious candidates. There is no substitute for face-to-face time and ad-hoc meetings. The primary mentor would commit to at least two hours of one-on-one coaching every week, probably two breakfasts or evening meetings. Each Intern would also be assigned three other mentors that focus on specific areas: one for coding, one for security testing and one for security architecture / technology. The coding mentor would help them develop great coding skills, the testing mentor great code review and hacking skills and the architecture coach work through technical specifics like cryptography or SAML. Each secondary mentor would meet via a Google Hangout with the Intern for one hour a week and provide additional support as needed. For one week during the six month internship period the Intern would then also spend one full week physically with each secondary mentor at their work location. Candidates would almost definanely need to be located in the States and be legal US citizens (unless we could set this up globally of course).</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='Living expenses, great equipment, great mentors and the ability to work on a reference able open source code base should be enough to attract the very best, brightest and most motivated talent out there.'>Using 100% of the sponsorship money for the proogram each Intern would get paid a living allowance of say $2,000 USD a month, healthcare and get a travel allowance for expenses while on the road at the secondary mentors locations. I estimate that it would cost $4K a month per Intern and so around 10 sponsors at $10,000 each would turn out 4 Interns a year. Each Intern would get all the equipment and tools they need to be successful including a brand new MacBook to keep if they successfully graduate and fully expensed accounts on GitHub, AWS etc. for the period of the program. Each Intern would be expected to work on projects as part of a scrum team building 100% open source software projects at Seconauts. That's right the underlying program would be shipping security related software that will be open source. There is no place like production. We would set meaningful and challenging tasks that advance the community and push the interns to learn and explore. People would work from an established backlog and would be free to hack on their own projects at weekends as well. Living expenses, great equipment, great mentors and the ability to work on a reference able open source code base should be enough to attract the very best, brightest and most motivated talent out there. </span></p>

<p>All Interns accepted into the program would be required to sign-up to work for one of the sponsors for 18 months after the program is completed. All sponsors (but only sponsors) would be able to make offers to candidates and they would choose the most suitable offer. This provides the incentive for sponsors to fund the program in the first place. $10,000 USD is generally less than the fees companies pay recruiters! At the end of the six months Interns would have learned how to ship secure code, review and fix broken code, design secure software with their understanding of core technologies like cryptography as well as a solid understanding and experience of the industry. Another way to read that is that they would be highly skilled and highly valuable (and of course in high demand).</p>

<p>At the end of the Internship, sponsors would be able to offer the Interns jobs.</p>

<p><strong>What's in it for sponsors?</strong></p>

<ul>
    <li>Invest in creating skills the industry needs</li>
    <li>Exclusive access to the interns for recruiting after the program finishes</li>
    <li>All sponsorship would be tax deductible via the 510(3)C</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>What's in it for the interns?</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Invaluable access and coaching to top industry mentors</li>
<li>6 months of pure software security training to develop skills in high demand</li>
<li>A public portfolio of work (code and blogs)</li>
<br />
<strong>What's in it for the mentors?</strong></br>
Brad Feld talks a lot about giving first and being rewarded later in his new book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1118441540/startuprev-20">Startup Communities</a>. Most successful people that I know value their time working on advisory boards and the personal relatinships from mentoring people as some of the most rewarding things they do. Any good mentor will have a busy schedule but paying it forward or paying it back will be a rewarding experience that will have an impact on the industry and on individuals lives. 
</br></br>
I know I would sign-up for something like this as a sponsor and as a mentor in a heart-beat. 15 years ago I would have applied in a heart-beat. A CSO for a major Internet company, an AppSec lead for a big financial services company and the CTO of a tools vendor have also said they would sign up to mentor I could pull this off. To top that three security services firms said they would sponsor a program like this and a core developer on the JQuery team has offered to participate if I could pull it off.
<strong>What about you?</strong>
</br></br>
[Thanks to <a href="http://www.twitter.com/mkonda">@mkonda</a> and <a href="http://www.twitter.com/mikedelibero">@mikedelibero</a> for their offline thoughts on this.]

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The new blog, OWASP &amp other notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://curphey.github.com/blog/2012/10/17/new-blog-owasp-and-other-notes/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-17T21:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://curphey.github.com/blog/2012/10/17/new-blog-owasp-and-other-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love Twitter but sometimes 140 characters just isn't enough. Let's be honest 140 characters is rarely enough for anything except your Lizard brain but the frictionless way of both sharing and reading snippets of information is so convenient that it is usually good enough for me. I do have a mental bank of notes that require co-herent sentences and so to light up the electrons of my new blog here goes:<!--more--></p>

<p><strong>I am a born again blogger :</strong> Yep siree, that's right, I have found religion and the deep value in both blogging and reading blogs again. I used to post regularly at SecurityBuddha.com and then for some reason less frequently when I moved the blog to www.curphey.com but posts have hydrated over the last few years. Until the end of this year I am all consumed with writing my Practical Software Security book but I am just loving the writing process and have every intention of returning to posting frequently.</p>

<p>You may also notice if you are here for the first time or you arrived here from a recent Twitter link that this is a shiny new blog created today with no archived content. You won't notice (at least not automagically) if you were previously subscribed to the RSS feed. I am very sorry that I have broken linkage but it was infact a concious decision. I decided that it was time for a brand new start. When I started importing old content and looked at the posts (some of which I had carried around for nearly a decade) I often cringed. I take full responsibility for previous posts and dont regret any I have changed a lot. I am thankful to those previous readers and of course hope they will continue but hope to find a new generation of readers and friends.</p>

<p>Yes, I will be prettifying it at some point!</p>

<p>For anyone interested this blog is powered by <a href="http://www.octopress.org">Octopress</a> and hosted using <a href="http://pages.github.com/">github Pages.</a> I am posting this using Sublime Text 2 and Terminal (rake generate and rake deploy). It's a simple setup but simply awesome!</p>

<p><strong>OWASP :</strong> I have been very critical of OWASP for the last few years. If you didn't know <a href="https://www.owasp.org/index.php/History_of_OWASP">I started it</a> back in 2002</a>. My consistent criticism has been generally around the focus and quality of projects, issues that might be attributed to OWASP's own success. The nature of the project (it's really more of a community than a project of course) is that it is totally open to absolutely anyone to participate. That attracts people from all backgrounds; those with deep skill and experience and some of those frankly without. It's also a fact that most humans like to start or create things but far fewer like to improve or maintain things. This (in my opinon) has resulted in OWASP becoming an umbrella for thousands of peoples ideas. Some become amazingly valuable projects and are actively maintained (the ZAP Proxy is a great example) but many are not. As a result it is left to users to filter the signal from the noise. I think and I hear from many people that there is way too much noise that simply drowns out the quaity signals.</p>

<p>When I started OWASP I hoped it would become a community for security people and software developers to work together solving common software security problems. What is has evolved into in my opinion is a community of security folks mainly involved in testing and mainly involved in operational security. I lobbied behind the scenes, I poked and I prodded in a variety of places trying to make OWASP a place that I considered attractive for developers but was unable to effect the change I wanted to see. Selecting SourceForge as a project hosting site in 2010 is hardly an act that inspires modern developers to engage. You don't get hired from your SourceForge activity you know! Starting a project with a goal of making commercial development frameworks more secure without being able to articulate the gaps in current frameworks and not having a single person on the project team that had actually shipped a commerical framework just made no sense to me. I have never questioned the intentions, there are all good people, just the decisions. It is also important to say that these are just two examples of many and I appreciate that it is very easy to throw stones. When combined with people constantly mailing me tales of beuracracy and politics, I got frustrated, dissapointed and became disillusioned. OWASP simply stopped being fun for me. I gave up trying to make it what I wanted it to be and I moved on.</p>

<p>I am very proud to have been a part of launching a successful global community and thankful for the opportunities that have come my way as a result of it. I check in on the site from time to time, love exchanging mails and drinking beer with people I have met along the way and sometimes get dragged into offline discusions wth passionate people who also want to change the status quo, but for the most part OWASP isn't an important source of information for me anymore. To be clear I am not saying that it isn't doing important or relevant work but I am saying that it is doing things that just things that aren't important to me. The other day I wanted to ask for opinions on the security of a Grails Plugin and the week before about entropy for creating an API key. <span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='key exchange algorithms (such as Diffie-Hellman for SSL)&#8230;.allow use to safely exchange encryption keys with an unknown party'>I wanted opinions about architecture, cryptographic algorithms and engineering patterns. The <a href="https://www.owasp.org/index.php/Guide_to_Cryptography#Key_Exchange_Algorithms"></a>OWASP Guide to Cryptography</a> says that key exchange algorithms (such as Diffie-Hellman for SSL)....allow use to safely exchange encryption keys with an unknown party. An unknown party, I sincerley hope not! </span>The noise and low quality combined with a lack of personal time to filter out the noise from the signal means that I rarely reference any of the content any more.</p>

<p>So with that said you might think I would be smirking when I see people Tweeting that they are abstaining from the OWASP Elections because they want fundamental change but actually nothing could be further from the truth. I am of course a little saddened but I have come to reason with myself that the state of OWASP is just fine. I don't vote as I am not a member but as a community of pre-dominantly IT security folks that are predominantly interested in security testing and in raising awareness of the state of insecure web applications to the IT industry, OWASP is doing a fantastic job. <span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='A &#8216;Jack of all trades&#8217; is a master of none.&#8221;'>I have also come to reason with myself that if you changed the way the project operates then the groundswell of people involved would just go elsewhere and do the same thing somewhere else. We have learnt that lesson from bit torents. I used to think that developers and security people would mingle, cross polinate and be one big happy family but now think that they are fundamentaly driven by such different motivations and operate with such different cultures that a single project catering to both is simply naive. A 'Jack of all trades' is a master of none." </span>. Trust me, some days I daydream of becoming Chair again, conducting a Larry Page style spring clean of the cruft, banishing the res-tape and petty politics I hear about and actively attracting developers, But I have also come to reason that if you did that you would alientate the very thing that has made OWASP what it is today, the OWASP community.</p>

<p>I think there is room for a different type of software security community and I am going to create it. It will be called Seconauts. I don't think anyone should see it as competitive and I will work hard to make it complimentary. It will be primarily for developers, initially invite only and focus on a small number (curated) high quality projects. Initially we are going to put Arachni Scanner online as a free managed services that will be 100% privacy aware (i.e. we wil lnever know who you are scanning or what the findings are) as well as a git based security knowledge sharing system (think GitHub for software security). The book will also be published open source online for free at Seconauts in the new year. Over the last year several of us have been making slow but steady progress but it's time to step on the gas. I have a lawyer working on the 501(C)3 status and plan to start calling around to raise sponsorship money in the coming weeks. 100% of that money will go to pay developers to build 100% open source code. 0% admin overhead. The site really should be pushed live in beta in a few weeks (right Mike!).</p>

<p>So much like with the US elections, if you can vote in the OWASP elections then you should. If none of the candidates represent a vision that you want then you should either throw your hat in the ring or go off and create what you want elesewhere (like I am doing) but in practical terms abstaining is a vote for no change.</p>

<p>For those who may say "you have changed your tune haven't you?", well sure. Maybe I have mellowed, maybe I am aging well or maybe I just see things a little differently these days but one thing is for sure, I absolutley see the need for a different type of software security and I am going to launch it. There are questions I need answered, topics I want to see discussed and open source software I want to see built!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
