<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: OWASP | Mark Curphey]]></title>
  <link href="http://curphey.github.com/blog/categories/owasp/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://curphey.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-04T14:41:31-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://curphey.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mark Curphey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The new blog, OWASP &amp other notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://curphey.github.com/blog/2012/10/17/new-blog-owasp-and-other-notes/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-17T21:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://curphey.github.com/blog/2012/10/17/new-blog-owasp-and-other-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I love Twitter but sometimes 140 characters just isn't enough. Let's be honest 140 characters is rarely enough for anything except your Lizard brain but the frictionless way of both sharing and reading snippets of information is so convenient that it is usually good enough for me. I do have a mental bank of notes that require co-herent sentences and so to light up the electrons of my new blog here goes:<!--more--></p>

<p><strong>I am a born again blogger :</strong> Yep siree, that's right, I have found religion and the deep value in both blogging and reading blogs again. I used to post regularly at SecurityBuddha.com and then for some reason less frequently when I moved the blog to www.curphey.com but posts have hydrated over the last few years. Until the end of this year I am all consumed with writing my Practical Software Security book but I am just loving the writing process and have every intention of returning to posting frequently.</p>

<p>You may also notice if you are here for the first time or you arrived here from a recent Twitter link that this is a shiny new blog created today with no archived content. You won't notice (at least not automagically) if you were previously subscribed to the RSS feed. I am very sorry that I have broken linkage but it was infact a concious decision. I decided that it was time for a brand new start. When I started importing old content and looked at the posts (some of which I had carried around for nearly a decade) I often cringed. I take full responsibility for previous posts and dont regret any I have changed a lot. I am thankful to those previous readers and of course hope they will continue but hope to find a new generation of readers and friends.</p>

<p>Yes, I will be prettifying it at some point!</p>

<p>For anyone interested this blog is powered by <a href="http://www.octopress.org">Octopress</a> and hosted using <a href="http://pages.github.com/">github Pages.</a> I am posting this using Sublime Text 2 and Terminal (rake generate and rake deploy). It's a simple setup but simply awesome!</p>

<p><strong>OWASP :</strong> I have been very critical of OWASP for the last few years. If you didn't know <a href="https://www.owasp.org/index.php/History_of_OWASP">I started it</a> back in 2002</a>. My consistent criticism has been generally around the focus and quality of projects, issues that might be attributed to OWASP's own success. The nature of the project (it's really more of a community than a project of course) is that it is totally open to absolutely anyone to participate. That attracts people from all backgrounds; those with deep skill and experience and some of those frankly without. It's also a fact that most humans like to start or create things but far fewer like to improve or maintain things. This (in my opinon) has resulted in OWASP becoming an umbrella for thousands of peoples ideas. Some become amazingly valuable projects and are actively maintained (the ZAP Proxy is a great example) but many are not. As a result it is left to users to filter the signal from the noise. I think and I hear from many people that there is way too much noise that simply drowns out the quaity signals.</p>

<p>When I started OWASP I hoped it would become a community for security people and software developers to work together solving common software security problems. What is has evolved into in my opinion is a community of security folks mainly involved in testing and mainly involved in operational security. I lobbied behind the scenes, I poked and I prodded in a variety of places trying to make OWASP a place that I considered attractive for developers but was unable to effect the change I wanted to see. Selecting SourceForge as a project hosting site in 2010 is hardly an act that inspires modern developers to engage. You don't get hired from your SourceForge activity you know! Starting a project with a goal of making commercial development frameworks more secure without being able to articulate the gaps in current frameworks and not having a single person on the project team that had actually shipped a commerical framework just made no sense to me. I have never questioned the intentions, there are all good people, just the decisions. It is also important to say that these are just two examples of many and I appreciate that it is very easy to throw stones. When combined with people constantly mailing me tales of beuracracy and politics, I got frustrated, dissapointed and became disillusioned. OWASP simply stopped being fun for me. I gave up trying to make it what I wanted it to be and I moved on.</p>

<p>I am very proud to have been a part of launching a successful global community and thankful for the opportunities that have come my way as a result of it. I check in on the site from time to time, love exchanging mails and drinking beer with people I have met along the way and sometimes get dragged into offline discusions wth passionate people who also want to change the status quo, but for the most part OWASP isn't an important source of information for me anymore. To be clear I am not saying that it isn't doing important or relevant work but I am saying that it is doing things that just things that aren't important to me. The other day I wanted to ask for opinions on the security of a Grails Plugin and the week before about entropy for creating an API key. <span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='key exchange algorithms (such as Diffie-Hellman for SSL)&#8230;.allow use to safely exchange encryption keys with an unknown party'>I wanted opinions about architecture, cryptographic algorithms and engineering patterns. The <a href="https://www.owasp.org/index.php/Guide_to_Cryptography#Key_Exchange_Algorithms"></a>OWASP Guide to Cryptography</a> says that key exchange algorithms (such as Diffie-Hellman for SSL)....allow use to safely exchange encryption keys with an unknown party. An unknown party, I sincerley hope not! </span>The noise and low quality combined with a lack of personal time to filter out the noise from the signal means that I rarely reference any of the content any more.</p>

<p>So with that said you might think I would be smirking when I see people Tweeting that they are abstaining from the OWASP Elections because they want fundamental change but actually nothing could be further from the truth. I am of course a little saddened but I have come to reason with myself that the state of OWASP is just fine. I don't vote as I am not a member but as a community of pre-dominantly IT security folks that are predominantly interested in security testing and in raising awareness of the state of insecure web applications to the IT industry, OWASP is doing a fantastic job. <span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='A &#8216;Jack of all trades&#8217; is a master of none.&#8221;'>I have also come to reason with myself that if you changed the way the project operates then the groundswell of people involved would just go elsewhere and do the same thing somewhere else. We have learnt that lesson from bit torents. I used to think that developers and security people would mingle, cross polinate and be one big happy family but now think that they are fundamentaly driven by such different motivations and operate with such different cultures that a single project catering to both is simply naive. A 'Jack of all trades' is a master of none." </span>. Trust me, some days I daydream of becoming Chair again, conducting a Larry Page style spring clean of the cruft, banishing the res-tape and petty politics I hear about and actively attracting developers, But I have also come to reason that if you did that you would alientate the very thing that has made OWASP what it is today, the OWASP community.</p>

<p>I think there is room for a different type of software security community and I am going to create it. It will be called Seconauts. I don't think anyone should see it as competitive and I will work hard to make it complimentary. It will be primarily for developers, initially invite only and focus on a small number (curated) high quality projects. Initially we are going to put Arachni Scanner online as a free managed services that will be 100% privacy aware (i.e. we wil lnever know who you are scanning or what the findings are) as well as a git based security knowledge sharing system (think GitHub for software security). The book will also be published open source online for free at Seconauts in the new year. Over the last year several of us have been making slow but steady progress but it's time to step on the gas. I have a lawyer working on the 501(C)3 status and plan to start calling around to raise sponsorship money in the coming weeks. 100% of that money will go to pay developers to build 100% open source code. 0% admin overhead. The site really should be pushed live in beta in a few weeks (right Mike!).</p>

<p>So much like with the US elections, if you can vote in the OWASP elections then you should. If none of the candidates represent a vision that you want then you should either throw your hat in the ring or go off and create what you want elesewhere (like I am doing) but in practical terms abstaining is a vote for no change.</p>

<p>For those who may say "you have changed your tune haven't you?", well sure. Maybe I have mellowed, maybe I am aging well or maybe I just see things a little differently these days but one thing is for sure, I absolutley see the need for a different type of software security and I am going to launch it. There are questions I need answered, topics I want to see discussed and open source software I want to see built!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
